<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/songscapes.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://relaxng.org/ns/structure/1.0"?>
<?xml-model href="../schema/songscapes.rng" type="application/xml" schematypens="http://purl.oclc.org/dsdl/schematron"?>
<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude">
  <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Ayres and Dialogues, For One, Two, and Three Voyces</title>
              <title type="description">Front matter</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <publicationStmt>
            <p>Early Modern Songscapes</p>
         </publicationStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <bibl>
              <title>Ayres and Dialogues, For One, Two, and Three Voyces</title>
              <author role="writer">Henry Lawes</author>
              <author role="poet">Edmund Waller</author>
              <author role="poet">Francis Finch</author>
              <author role="poet">Edmund Waller</author>
              <author role="poet">Will Barker</author>
              <author role="poet">Thomas Norton</author>
              <author role="poet">John Cobb</author>
              <author role="poet">John Phillips</author>
              <author role="poet">John Carwarden</author>
              <author role="poet">Edmund Waller</author>
              <pubPlace>London</pubPlace>, <date type="publication" when="1653">1653</date>.
              <idno type="wing">L638</idno>
              <idno type="call_number">Folger L638, copy 1</idno>
              <biblScope unit="leaf" from="a1r" to="A2r">leaves a1 recto to A2 recto</biblScope>,
            </bibl>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
  </teiHeader>
  <text>
  <front>
          <titlePage rend="center">
            <docTitle>
              <titlePart type="main">AYRES AND DIALOGUES, For One, Two, and Three Voyces.</titlePart>
            </docTitle>
            <byline>BY <graphic url="#"><!-- engraving --></graphic> HENRY LAWES Servant to his late <choice><abbr>Ma:<hi rend="sup">tie</hi></abbr><expan>Majestie</expan></choice> in his publick and private Musick. W. Faitharne fecit</byline>
            <docEdition>The First Booke.</docEdition>
            <docImprint>LONDON, Printed by <hi rend="italic">T. H.</hi> for <hi rend="italic">John Playford,</hi> and are to be sold at his Shop, in the Inner Temple, near the Church door, <date>1653</date>.</docImprint>
          </titlePage>
        <div type="epistles"> <!--dedicatory epistles-->
  <pb n="a2r"/>
          <div type="epistle">
            <salute>
            <lb/>To the Right Honorable,
            <l>The two most Excellent Sisters,</l>
            <l><hi rend="italic">ALICE</hi> Countesse of <hi rend="italic">CARBERY,</hi></l>
            <l>And</l>
            <l><hi rend="italic">MARY</hi> Lady <hi rend="italic">HERBERT</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Cherbury</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Castle-Island,</hi></l>
            <l>Daughters to the Right Honorable, <hi rend="italic">John</hi> Earle of <hi rend="italic">Bridgewater,</hi> Lord President of <hi rend="italic">WALES,</hi> &amp;c.</l>
          </salute>
            <ab rend="italic">I Need not tell Your <hi rend="roman">Ladiships,</hi> that since my Attendance on His late <hi rend="roman">MAJESTY</hi> (my most Gracious Master) I have neglected the exercise of my Profession. Yet, to debarr Idlenesse (which, without vanity I may say, I was never passionatly in love with) I have made some <hi rend="roman">Compositions,</hi> which now I resolve to publish to the World. What Grounds and Motives lead me to this Publication, I conceive not so proper for your Ladiships notice, having elsewhere told it <hi rend="roman">to the Reader.</hi> But no sooner I thought of making these Publick, than of inscribing them to Your <hi rend="roman">Ladiships,</hi> most of them being Composed when I was employed by Your ever Honour'd Parents to attend Your <hi rend="roman">Ladishipp's</hi> Education in <hi rend="roman">Musick;</hi> who (as in other Accomplishments fit for Persons of Your Quality) excell'd most Ladies, especially in <hi rend="roman">Vocall Musick,</hi> wherin You were so absolute, that You gave Life and Honour to all I set and taught You; and that with more Vnderstanding than a new Generation pretending to Skil (I dare say) are Capable of. I could therefore do nothing more becomming my Gratitude than a Dedication of These (so much Your own) to both Your <hi rend="roman">Ladiships;</hi> and to manifest that Honour I bear to the Memory of Your deceased Parents, whose Favors it is impossible should ever be forgotten by</ab>
          <signed>
            <lb/>Your Ladiships most humbly devoted
            <l>Servant,</l>
            <l><hi rend="italic">HENRY LAWES.</hi></l>
          </signed>
        </div>
<!--a2v-->
        <div type="epistle">
          <salute>
            <l>To all Undersatnders or Lovers of MUSICK.</l>
          </salute>
            <ab rend="italic">It is easie to say I have been much importun'd, by Persons of Quality, to
              Publish my <hi rend="roman">Compositions:</hi> But though I could plead it (and without vain
              Pretensions) yet now I shall wave it. Nor was I drawn to it by any little thoughts of private Gain;
              though men of my Relations (as the World now goes) are justly presum'd not to overflow; and perhaps
              the matter will not reach that value, let the <hi rend="roman">Stationer</hi> look to that, who
              himselfe hath undergone the Charge and Trouble of the whole Impression; who yet (by his favour)
              hath lately made bold to print, in one Book, above twenty of my Songs, whereof I had no knowledge
              till his Book was in the Presse; and it seems he found those so acceptable that he is ready for more. Therefore now the Question is not, whether or no my <hi rend="roman">Compositions</hi> shall be Publick, but whether they shall come forth from me, or from some other hand; and which of the two is likeliest to afford the true correct Copies, I leave others to judge. In this Book I reprint none that were publish'd in the former, or ever in print before. I could tell ye also, I have often found many of mine that have walkt abroad in other mens names: how they came to lose their
              Relations and be Anabaptiz'd, I think not worth examining. Only I shall say, that some who so
              adopted and owned my Songs had greater kindnesse for the Children than for the Father; else sure
              they had not bestow'd some other late Ayres (which themsleves could not own) upon Forrainers and
              Strangers, because I <hi rend="roman">compos'd</hi> them to <hi rend="roman">Italian</hi> and
              <hi rend="roman">Spanish</hi> words. I should think such an Injury an unreasonable piece of
              Injustice, since now we live in so sullen an Age, that our Prefession it selfe hath lost its
              Incouragement. But Wise men have observ'd our Generation so giddy, that whatsoever is Native
              (be it never so excellent) must lose its taste, because themselves have lost theirs. For my part,
              I professe (and such as know me can bear me witnesse) I desire to render every man his due, whether
              Strangers or Natives. I acknowledge the <hi rend="roman">Italians</hi> the greatest Masters of
              Musick, but yet not all. And (without depressing the Honour of other Countries) I may say our own
              Nation hath had and yet hath as able Musitians as any in <hi rend="roman">Europe;</hi> and many
              now living (whose  names I forbear) are excellent both for the Voyce and Instruments. But as in
              Musick the <hi rend="roman">Unison</hi> and <hi rend="roman">Diapason</hi> are the sweetest of
              all <hi rend="roman">Chords,</hi> yet a <hi rend="roman">Second</hi> and a
              <hi rend="roman">Seventh,</hi> which stand next to them, are more <hi rend="roman">Discordant</hi>
              rom them than any other Notes in all the <hi rend="roman">Scale:</hi> So to Musicians, a man's
              next Neighbour is the farthest from him, and none give so harsh a Report of the
              <hi rend="roman">English</hi> as the <hi rend="roman">English</hi> themselves. We should not think
              Musick any stranger to this Island, since our Ancestors tell us that the
              <hi rend="roman">Britains</hi> had Musicians before they had Books; and the
              <hi rend="roman">Romans</hi> that invaded us (who were not too forward to magnifie other Nations)
              confesse what power the <hi rend="roman">Druids</hi> and <hi rend="roman">Bards</hi> had over the
              Peoples affections by recording in Songs the Deeds of Heroick Spirits, their very
              <hi rend="roman">Laws</hi> and <hi rend="roman">Religion</hi> being sung in Tunes, and so
              (without Letters) transmitted to Posterity; wherein it seems they were so dextrous, that their
              Neighbours out of <hi rend="roman">Gaul</hi> came hither to learn it. How their Successors held it
               up I know not: But King <hi rend="roman">Henry</hi> the Eight did much advance it, especially in
                the former part of his Reign, when his minde was more intent upon Arts and Sciences, at which
                time he invited all the greatest Masters out of <hi rend="roman">Italy</hi> and other Countries,
                and Himselfe gave example by <hi rend="roman">Composing</hi> with his own hand two intire
                 <hi rend="roman">Services,</hi> which were often sung in his Chappell, as the Lord
                 <hi rend="roman">Herbert</hi> of <hi rend="roman">Cherbury</hi> (who writ his Life) hath
                 left upon Record. Since whose time it prosper'd much in the Reign of Queen
                 <hi rend="roman">Elizabeth,</hi> King <hi rend="roman">James,</hi> and His late
                 <hi rend="roman">Majesty.</hi> I confesse the Italian Language may have some advantage by being
                 better smooth'd and <hi rend="roman">vowell'd</hi> for Musick, which I found by many Songs which
                 I set to <hi rend="roman">Italian</hi> words: and our English seems a
<pb n="b1r"/>
            little over-clogg'd with <hi rend="roman">Consonants;</hi> but that's much the <hi rend="roman">Composer's</hi> fault, who by judicious setting and right tuning the words may make it smooth enough. And since our palates are so much after Novelties, I desir'd to try the <hi rend="roman">Greek,</hi> having never seen any thing <hi rend="roman">Set</hi> in that Language by our own Musicians or Strangers; and (by <hi rend="roman">Composing</hi> some of <hi rend="roman">Anacreon's</hi> Odes) I found the Greek Tongue full as good as any for Musick, and in some particulars sweeter than the <hi rend="roman">Latine,</hi> or those Moderne ones that descended from <hi rend="roman">Latine.</hi> I never lov'd to <hi rend="roman">Set</hi> or sing words which I do not understand; and where I cannot, I desir'd help of others who were able to interpret. But this present Generation is so sated with what's Native, that nothing takes their eare but what's sung in a Language which (commonly) they understand as little as they do the Musick. And to make them a little sensible of this ridiculous humour, I took a <hi rend="roman">Table</hi> or <hi rend="roman">Index</hi> of old <hi rend="roman">Italian</hi> Songs (for one, two, and three Voyces) and this <hi rend="roman">Index</hi> (which read together made a strange medley of Non-sense) I set to a varyed Ayre, and gave out that it came from <hi rend="roman">Italy,</hi> whereby it hath passed for a rare <hi rend="roman">Italian</hi> Song. This very Song I have now here printed. And if this First Book shall find acceptance, I intend yearly to publish the like; for I confess I have a sufficient Stock lying by me (and shall compose more) having had the Honour to <hi rend="roman">Set</hi> the Verses of the most and chiefest Poets of our Times. As for those Copies of Verses in this Book, I have rendred their Names who made them, from whose hands I received them. These Reasons (with some other not here mentioned) drew me forth to this Publication, which if receiv'd with the same heart that I offer it, with be further Encouragement for</ab>
          <signed>
            H.L.
          </signed>
        </div>
        </div>
<!--b1v-->
    <div type="commendatory_verse">
      <div type="commendatory">
          <salute>
            To Mr. HENRY LAWES, who had then newly set a Song of mine in the Year, 1635.
          </salute>
          <lg type="stanza" rend="italic">
            <l>VErse makes Heroick Vertue live,</l>
            <l>But you can life to Verses give:</l>
            <l>As when in open aire we blow</l>
            <l>The breath (though strain'd) sounds flat and low,</l>
            <l>But if a Trumpet take the blast,</l>
            <l>It lifts it high, and makes it last:</l>
            <l>So in your Ayres our Numbers drest</l>
            <l>Make a shrill sally from the Brest</l>
            <l>Of Nymphs, who singing what we pen'd,</l>
            <l>Our Passions to themselves commend,</l>
            <l>While Love Victorious with thy Art</l>
            <l>Governs at once their Voyce and Heart.</l>
            <l>You by the help of Tune and Time</l>
            <l>Can make that Song which was but Rime.</l>
            <l> <hi rend="roman">NOY</hi> pleading, no man doubts the Cause,</l>
            <l>Or questions Verses set by <hi rend="roman">LAWES.</hi></l>
            <l>For as a window thick with paint</l>
            <l>Lets in a light but dim and faint,</l>
            <l>So others with Division hide</l>
            <l>The Lights of Sense, the Poets Pride,</l>
            <l>But you alone may truly boast</l>
            <l>That not a syllable is lost;</l>
            <l>The Writer's and the Setter's skill</l>
            <l>At once the ravish't Eare do fill.</l>
            <l>Let those which only warble long,</l>
            <l>And gargle in their throats a Song,</l>
            <l>Content themselves with <hi rend="roman">Ut, re, mi,</hi></l>
            <l>Let words and sense by set by Thee.</l>
          </lg>
        <signed>
          ED. WALLER, <hi rend="italic">Esquire.</hi>
        </signed>
      </div>
<!--b2r-->
        <div type="commendatory">
          <salute>
          To his Honour'd F. Mr. <hi rend="italic">HENRY LAWES,</hi> on his <hi rend="italic">Ayres</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Dialogues.</hi>
          </salute>
          <lg type="stanza" rend="italic">
            <l>THose happy few who apprehend thy flight,</l>
            <l>Ever above the Cloud, yet still in sight,</l>
            <l>Cannot by all their Numbers and Addresse</l>
            <l>Swell or advance thy praises, but confesse.</l>
            <l>For thou art fix'd beyond the Power of Fate,</l>
            <l>Since nothing that is Mortal can Create.</l>
            <l>And it is possible that thou should'st dye</l>
            <l>Who can'st bestow such Immortality?</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="stanza" rend="italic">
            <l>I have not sought the Rules by which yee try</l>
            <l>When a <hi rend="roman">Chord</hi> broke, or holds in <hi rend="roman">Harmony;</hi></l>
            <l>But I am sure Thou hast a Soul within</l>
            <l>As if created for a <hi rend="roman">Cherubin;</hi></l>
            <l>Brim full of Candour and wise Innocence,</l>
            <l>And is not Musick a Resultance thence?</l>
            <l>For sure the blunt-bill'd Swan's first fame to sing</l>
            <l>Sprung from the motion of her spotless Wing.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="stanza" rend="italic">
            <l>But sole Integrity winns not the Cause,</l>
            <l>For then each honest man would be a <hi rend="roman">LAWES:</hi></l>
            <l>Thou hast deep Iudgement, Phansie, and high Sence;</l>
            <l>Old and new Wit, steady Experience;</l>
            <l>A Soul unbrib'd by any thing but Fame;</l>
            <l>Grasping to get nought but a good great Name.</l>
            <l>Hence all thy <hi rend="roman">Ayres</hi> flow pure and unconfin'd,</l>
            <l>Blown by no Mercenary <hi rend="roman">Lapland</hi> Wind,</l>
            <l>And so transmitted to Posteritie,</l>
            <l>Which never shall their well-grown Honor blast,</l>
            <l>Since they  have Thy, that's the best, Iudgement past.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="stanza" rend="italic">
            <l>Yet Some, who forc'd t'admire Thee, must repine</l>
            <l>The Sence so humour'd, and those Humours hit,</l>
            <l>Will call them acts of  <hi rend="roman">Fortune,</hi> not of <hi rend="roman">Wit;</hi></l>
            <l>Hoping their want of Skill may be thy Brand</l>
            <l>'Cause they have not the Luck to Understand;</l>
            <l>Cry up the  <hi rend="roman">Words</hi> to cry  <hi rend="roman">Thee</hi> down, and sweare</l>
            <l>Thou  <hi rend="roman">sett'st</hi> more  <hi rend="roman">Sence</hi> then they can meet elsewhere,</l>
            <l>Concluding could themselves such  <hi rend="roman">Verses</hi> show</l>
            <l>They could produce such  <hi rend="roman">Compositions</hi> too.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="stanza" rend="italic">
            <l>But is't thy fault if the great Witts whole Quire</l>
            <l>Before all Others still prefer Thy Lyre?</l>
            <l>They tasted All, and Thine among the rest,</l>
            <l>But then return'd to Thee, 'cause Best was Best.</l>
            <l>Bid such attach Thy Old <hi rend="roman">Anacreon's</hi> Greek,</l>
            <l>Where the least <hi rend="roman">Accent</hi> will cost Them a Week,</l>
            <l>Six Months a <hi rend="roman">Verse,</hi> and that Verse tun'd and scann'd</l>
            <l>(Though short) twelve Years, an Age to <hi rend="roman">Understand:</hi></l>
            <l>But thy Lute, like th'last Trump, hath rais'd His Head,</l>
            <l>Who, er'e the <hi rend="roman">Græcian Empire</hi> born, was dead.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="stanza" rend="italic">
            <l>Then let all Poetts bring all Verse, which They</l>
            <l>May on thy Desk as on an Altar lay,</l>
            <l>Where kindled by that Touch thy Hand hath given,</l>
            <l>'Twill climb (whence Musick first came down) to Heaven.</l>
          </lg>
          <signed>
            FRANCIS FINCH, <hi rend="italic">Esquire.</hi>
          </signed>
        </div>
<!--b2v-->
        <div type="commendatory">
          <salute>
            To the much honour'd Mr. <hi rend="italic">HENRY LAWES</hi> on his Book of <hi rend="italic">Ayres.</hi>
          </salute>
          <lg type="stanza" rend="italic">
            <l>THat Princes dye not, they to Poetts owe;</l>
            <l>Poetts themselves do owe their Lives to You;</l>
            <l>Whose Phansies soon would stifle, and declare</l>
            <l>They could not breath unlesse you lent them Ayre.</l>
            <l>'Tis that inspires their Feet, which else but crawle</l>
            <l>As <hi rend="roman">Judges</hi> walk th' old Measures round the <hi rend="roman">Hall,</hi></l>
            <l>Untill the feather'd heels of Youth advance</l>
            <l>And raise their dull pace up into a Dance:</l>
            <l>Your Art such Motion to our Verses brings</l>
            <l>We can but give them Feet, You give them Wings.</l>
          </lg>
          <signed>
            WILL. BARKER
          </signed>
        </div>
        <div type="commendatory">
          <salute>
            To his much honour'd F. Mr. <hi rend="italic">HENRY LAWES,</hi> on his Book of <hi rend="italic">Ayres.</hi>
          </salute>
          <lg type="stanza" rend="italic">
            <l>FAther of Numbers, who hast still thought fit</l>
            <l>To tune thy selfe, and then <hi rend="roman">Set</hi> others Wit;</l>
            <l>Forgive my Zeale, who with my Sprig of Bayes</l>
            <l>For Silence were, when <hi rend="roman">LAWES</hi> is nam'd, a wrong,</l>
            <l>The Subject and the Master of all Song;</l>
            <l>Who ne'r dost dive for Pebbles, undermine</l>
            <l>Mountains to make old rusty Iron shine:</l>
            <l>But hast made Great things Greater, do'st dispense</l>
            <l>Lustre to Wit, by adding Sence to Sence.</l>
            <l>For Passions are not Passions, 'till they be</l>
            <l>Rais'd to that height, which they expect from Thee;</l>
            <l>And all this is thy selfe; Thy Name's not grown</l>
            <l>Broader by putting on a Cap or Gown;</l>
            <l>Who like those Jockies that do often sell</l>
            <l>An old worn Jade, because he's saddled well:</l>
            <l>No; Thou can'st humour all that Wit can teach,</l>
            <l>Which those that are but Note-men cannot reach:</l>
            <l>Thou'rt all so fit, that some have pass'd their Votes,</l>
            <l>Thy Notes beget the Words, not Words thy Notes.</l>
          </lg>
          <signed>
            T. NORTON.
          </signed>
        </div>
<!--A1r-->
        <div type="commendatory">
          <salute>
            To my ever honour'd Friend &amp; Father, Mr. <hi rend="italic">HENRY LAWES,</hi> on his Book of <hi rend="italic">Ayres</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Dialogues.</hi>
          </salute>
          <lg type="stanza" rend="italic">
            <l>FAther of <hi rend="roman">Musick</hi> and <hi rend="roman">Musitians</hi> too,</l>
            <l>And Father of the <hi rend="roman">Muses,</hi> All's thy due:</l>
            <l>For not a drop that flows from <hi rend="roman">Helicon</hi></l>
            <l>But <hi rend="roman">Ayr'd</hi> by thee grows streight into a Song.</l>
            <l>So as when Light about the World was spread,</l>
            <l>All kind of Colours, Black, White, Green, and Red,</l>
            <l>Soon mixt with Substances, and grew to be,</l>
            <l>Plants, Grasse, and Flowrs, which All's but <hi rend="roman">Harmony.</hi></l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="stanza" rend="italic">
            <l>Thou mak'st the <hi rend="roman">Grave</hi> and <hi rend="roman">Light</hi> together chime,</l>
            <l>Both joyntly dance, yet keep their own true time;</l>
            <l>The winning <hi rend="roman">Dorick,</hi> that best loves the Harp;</l>
            <l>The <hi rend="roman">Phrygian,</hi> thats as sweet, though far more sharp;</l>
            <l>The brisk <hi rend="roman">Ionick,</hi> sober <hi rend="roman">Lydian</hi> Mood,</l>
            <l>Which every eare sucks in, and cryes, 'tis good:</l>
            <l>Thou hitt'st them all; their <hi rend="roman">Spirit, Tone,</hi> and <hi rend="roman">Pause,</hi></l>
            <l>Have all conspir'd to meet and honour <hi rend="roman">LAWES.</hi></l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="stanza" rend="italic">
            <l>No pointing <hi rend="roman">Comma, Colon,</hi> halfe so well</l>
            <l>Renders the Breath of Sense; they cannot tell</l>
            <l>The just Proportion how each word should go,</l>
            <l>To rise and fall, run swiftly or march slow;</l>
            <l>Thou shew'st 'tis <hi rend="roman">Musick</hi> only must do this,</l>
            <l>Which as though handlest it can never miss;</l>
            <l>All may be <hi rend="roman">Sung</hi> or <hi rend="roman">Read,</hi> which thou hast drest,</l>
            <l>Both are the same, save that the <hi rend="roman">Singing's</hi> best.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="stanza" rend="italic">
            <l>Thy Muse can make this sad, raise that to Life,</l>
            <l>Inflaming one, smoothing down th'others Strife,</l>
            <l>Meer Words, when measur'd best, are Words alone,</l>
            <l>Till quickned by their nearest Friend a Tone:</l>
            <l>And then, when <hi rend="roman">Sense</hi> and perfect <hi rend="roman">Concords</hi> mee<corr>t</corr></l>
            <l>Though th' Story bitter be, Tunes make it sweet:</l>
            <l>Thy <hi rend="roman">Ariadne's</hi> Grief's so fitly shown</l>
            <l>As bring's us <hi rend="roman">Pleasure</hi> from her saddest <hi rend="roman">Groan.</hi></l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="stanza" rend="italic">
            <l>And all this is thine own, thy true-born Heir;</l>
            <l>Nor stoln at home, nor Forrain far-fetcht Ware</l>
            <l>Made good by Mountebanks, who loud must cry</l>
            <l>Till some believe, and do as dearly buy;</l>
            <l>Which when they've try'd, not better nor yet more</l>
            <l>They find, than what does grown at their own door.</l>
            <l>For when such Mountains swell with mighty Birth,</l>
            <l>Wee find some poor small petty thing creep forth.</l>
          </lg>
          <lg type="stanza" rend="italic">
            <l>But I'm too short to speak thee, I've no Praise</l>
            <l>To give, but what I gather from thy Bayes:</l>
            <l>My narrow Hive's supply'd from they full Flow'r,</l>
            <l>Nor does thy Ocean Praise know Bank or Shoar:</l>
            <l>Yet this I dare attest, that who shall look</l>
            <l>And understand as well as read thy Book</l>
            <l>Must say that here both <hi rend="roman">Wit</hi> and <hi rend="roman">Musick</hi> meet;</l>
            <l>Like the great Giant's Riddle <hi rend="roman">Strong and Sweet.</hi></l>
          </lg>
        <signed>
        JOHN COBB.
        </signed>
      </div>
<!--A1v-->
      <div type="commendatory">
        <salute>
          TO his Honour'd Friend, Mr. <hi rend="italic">Henry Lawes,</hi> upon his Book of <hi rend="italic">Ayres.</hi>
        </salute>
        <lg type="stanza" rend="italic">
          <l>MUsick thou Soul of Verse, gently inspire,</l>
          <l rend="indent1">My untun'd Phansie with some sprightly <hi rend="roman">Ayre,</hi></l>
          <l>'Tis fittest now that I thy ayd require</l>
          <l rend="indent1">While I to sing thee and thy <hi rend="roman">Lawes</hi> prepare:</l>
          <l rend="indent3">For the high Raptures of a lofty strain</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Charm equall with the Bowr's <hi rend="roman">Aonian.</hi></l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza" rend="italic">
          <l>'Twere in me rudeness, not to blazon forth</l>
          <l rend="indent1">(Father in <hi rend="roman">Musick</hi>) thy deserved praise,</l>
          <l>Who oft have been, to witness thy rare worth,</l>
          <l rend="indent1">A ravish't hearer of thy skilfull Lay's.</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Thy Lay's that wont to lend a soaring wing,</l>
          <l rend="indent3">And to my tardy Muse fresh ardour bring.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza" rend="italic">
          <l>While brightest <hi rend="roman">Dames,</hi> the splendour of the Court,</l>
          <l rend="indent1">Themselves a silent <hi rend="roman">Musick</hi> to the Eye,</l>
          <l>Would oft to hear thy solemn <hi rend="roman">Ayres</hi> resort,</l>
          <l rend="indent1">Making thereby a double Harmony:</l>
          <l rend="indent3">'Tis hard to judge which adds the most delight,</l>
          <l rend="indent3">To th' Eare thy Charms, or theirs unto the Sight.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza" rend="italic">
          <l>But this is sure, had <hi rend="roman">Strada's</hi> Nightingale</l>
          <l rend="indent1">Heard the soft murmurs of thy <hi rend="roman">Ayry Lute,</hi></l>
          <l>She doubting left her own sweet voyce should fail</l>
          <l rend="indent1">To hear thy sweeter <hi rend="roman">Ayres,</hi> had quite been mute.</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Such Vertue dwels in Harmony divine</l>
          <l rend="indent3">(Admired <hi rend="roman">LAWES</hi>) and above all in thine.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza" rend="italic">
          <l>The <hi rend="roman">Dorick</hi> Sage, and the mild <hi rend="roman">Lydian,</hi></l>
          <l rend="indent1">The sad <hi rend="roman">Laconick</hi> unto Wars exciting,</l>
          <l>Th' <hi rend="roman">Aeolian</hi> Grave, the <hi rend="roman">Phrygian</hi> mournfull strain,</l>
          <l rend="indent1">The smooth <hi rend="roman">Jonick</hi> carelesly delighting,</l>
          <l rend="indent3">There calmly meet, and chearfully agree,</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Various themselves, to maek one Symphony.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza" rend="italic">
          <l>If we long since could boast thy purest vain,</l>
          <l rend="indent1">More then old <hi rend="roman">Greece</hi> the <hi rend="roman">Rhodopsian</hi> Lyre,</l>
          <l>Or <hi rend="roman">Latian</hi> Bowres of late <hi rend="roman">Marenzo's</hi> strain,</l>
          <l rend="indent1">How much must our applause advance thee higher?</l>
          <l rend="indent3">When thy yet more harmonious birth shall bring</l>
          <l rend="indent3">To us new Joyes, new Pleasures to the Spring.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza" rend="italic">
          <l>The Woods wild Songsters, wonder will surprize</l>
          <l rend="indent1">Hearing the sweet Art of they well tun'd Notes,</l>
          <l>What new unsonted chime? 'tis that outvies</l>
          <l rend="indent1">The Native sweetness of their liquid throats,</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Which while in vain they strive to æmulate</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Anothers <hi rend="roman">Musick's</hi> Duell they'l create.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza" rend="italic">
          <l>Whether pure Anthem's fill the sacred Quire,</l>
          <l rend="indent1">r Lady's Chambers the Lute's trembling voice,</l>
          <l>Or Rurall Song's the Country Swains admire,</l>
          <l rend="indent1">Thy large Invention still affords us choice;</l>
          <l rend="indent3">'Tis to thy Skill, that we indebted are,</l>
          <l rend="indent3">What ever Musick hath of neat and rare.</l>
        </lg>
        <lg type="stanza" rend="italic">
          <l>To thee the choycest Witts of <hi rend="roman">England</hi> owe</l>
          <l rend="indent1">The Life of their fam'd Verse, that ne'r shall dye,</l>
          <l>For thou hast made their rich conceits to flow</l>
          <l rend="indent1">In streams more rich to lasting memory,</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Such <hi rend="roman">Musick</hi> needs must steal our souls away,</l>
          <l rend="indent3">Where Voice and Verse do meet, where Love and Phansie play.</l>
        </lg>
        <signed>
          EDWARD PHILLIPS.
        </signed>
      </div>
<!--A2r-->
      <div type="commendatory">
        <salute>
          To my Honour'd Friend, Mr. <hi rend="italic">Henry Lawes,</hi> upon his Book of <hi rend="italic">Ayres.</hi>
        </salute>
        <lg type="stanza" rend="italic">
          <l>To calm the rugged Ocean, and asswage</l>
          <l>The horrid tempests in their highest rage,</l>
          <l>To tame the wildest Beasts, to still the Winds</l>
          <l>And quell the fury of distemper'd minds,</l>
          <l>Making the Pensive merry, th' overjolly</l>
          <l>Composing to a sober Melancholy:</l>
          <l>These are th'effects of sacred harmonie;</l>
          <l>Which being an Art so well attain'd by thee,</l>
          <l>(Most Honour'd <hi rend="roman">Laws</hi>) what can we less then number</l>
          <l>Thy Works with theirs who were the Ancients wonder?</l>
          <l>And give thee equall praise; but I forget;</l>
          <l>For we do owe thee a far greater debt,</l>
          <l>The charming sweetness of whose shorter Lay's,</l>
          <l>Not only we do hear with great amaze,</l>
          <l>But they have low descended to the deep,</l>
          <l>And wak'ned <hi rend="roman">Theseus</hi> Queen from <hi rend="roman">Stygian</hi> sleep;</l>
          <l>Who slighting <hi rend="roman">Orpheus,</hi> comes to beg of thee</l>
          <l>To ayd her with thy pow'rfull harmonie,</l>
          <l>Knowing thy strains more truly can expresse</l>
          <l>Her sense of <hi rend="roman">Theseus</hi> strange forgetfulnesse;</l>
          <l>Which makes us here to double thy Renown;</l>
          <l>Hereafter thou shalt wear fair <hi rend="roman">Ariadne's</hi> Crown.</l>
        </lg>
        <signed>
          JOHN PHILLIPS.
        </signed>
      </div>
      <div type="commendatory">
        <salute rend="italic">
          To my Dear and Honour'd Friend, Mr. <hi rend="roman">HENRY LAWES,</hi> upon his Incomparable Book of Songs.
        </salute>
        <lg type="stanza">
          <l>I Am no Poet, yet I will rhearse</l>
          <l>My Virgin Muse, though in unpolisht Verse.</l>
          <l>Perhaps the immature and lib'rall sence,</l>
          <l>(Yet better than those Ignorants commence,</l>
          <l>Who boldly dare their scandalous censures throw,</l>
          <l>And judge of things (I'le swear) they do not know)</l>
          <l>Will be to some unpleasing; but what then?</l>
          <l>Must they not know their wild pretensions, when</l>
          <l>Unnat'rally they'l raise a Forrain Name,</l>
          <l>And blast the Honour of their Native Fame?</l>
          <l>But stay; Will this reclaim them? No, th'are mad;</l>
          <l>Their Reason is infatuate, and clad</l>
          <l>In such a stupified ignorance:</l>
          <l>Nothing will please that is not come from <hi rend="italic">France</hi></l>
          <l>Or <hi rend="italic">Italy</hi>; but let them have their will,</l>
          <l>Whilst we unto thy Noble Art and Skill</l>
          <l>Do sacrifice our admirations:</l>
          <l>The tribute's j<corr>u</corr>st, and other Nations</l>
          <l>Cannot but pay it too, when they shall see</l>
          <l>Their best of Labours thus outdone by Thee;</l>
          <l>Or else amaz'd to see thy <hi rend="italic">English</hi> Ayre</l>
          <l>Past imitation; they will dispaire,</l>
          <l>And wonder we can surfeit with such meat,</l>
          <l>So rare, so rich, so pleasant, so compleat.</l>
          <l>Be happy then; Thou art above all hate;</l>
          <l>Thy great abil'ties have out-grown thy Fate.</l>
          <l>Thy Fortune soars aloft; thou art renown'd:</l>
          <l>Thy Fame's with Judgements approbation crown'd.</l>
          <l>And in this Verse, (as I disclaim all Wit)</l>
          <l>So 'twas thy worth, oblig'd my fancy t'it.</l>
        </lg>
        <signed rend="italic">
        JO. CARWARDEN
      </signed>
    </div>
</div>
<div type="table">
  <head rend="italic">The <hi rend="roman">TABLE,</hi> With the Names of those who were Authors of the Verses.</head>
     <ab>
       <hi rend="italic">A.</hi> <hi rend="italic">ARiadne</hi> <hi rend="italic">Pag.</hi> 1 - Mr. <hi rend="italic">William Cartwright</hi> of <hi rend="italic">Christ-Church Oxford.</hi>
         Am I dispis'd because you say 19 - Mr. <hi rend="italic">Robert Herick.</hi>
         <hi rend="italic">Amarantha</hi> sweet and fair 15 - Col. <hi rend="italic">Richard Lovelace.</hi>
         Ask me why I send you here 24 - Mr. <hi rend="italic">Herick.</hi>
      <hi rend="italic">B.</hi> Be gone, be gone thou perjur'd man 35 - <hi rend="italic">Henry Lawes.</hi>
      <hi rend="italic">C.</hi> Careless of Love, and free from Fears 11 - <hi rend="italic">Carew Raleigh,</hi> Esquire.
         <hi rend="italic">Chloris</hi> your self you so excell 14 - <hi rend="italic">Edmond Waller,</hi> Esquire.
         <hi rend="italic">Cælia</hi> thy bright Angel's Face 17 - <hi rend="italic">Thomas</hi> Earle of <hi rend="italic">Winchilsea.</hi>
         Canst thou love me, and yet doubt 23 - <hi rend="italic">William</hi> Earle of <hi rend="italic">Pembrooke.</hi>
         Come my <hi rend="italic">Lucasta</hi> 25 - Sir <hi rend="italic">Charles Lucas.</hi>
         Come heavy Souls 28 - Dr. <hi rend="italic">William Stroud,</hi> Oratour of the University of <hi rend="italic">Oxford.</hi>
         Come, come thou glorious Object 30 - Sir <hi rend="italic">William Killigrew.</hi>
         Come my Sweet whilst every strain 32 - Mr. <hi rend="italic">Cartwright.</hi>
      <hi rend="italic">D.</hi> Dearest do not now delay me 20 - Mr. <hi rend="italic">Henry Harington,</hi> Son to <hi rend="italic">Henry Harington.</hi>
      <hi rend="italic">F.</hi> Farewell fair Saint 10 - Mr, <hi rend="italic">Tho. Cary,</hi> Son to the Earle of Monmouth, and of the Bedchamber to his late Majesty.
      <hi rend="italic">G.</hi> Gaze not on Swann's 15 - Mr. <hi rend="italic">Henry Noel,</hi> Son to the L. Viscount <hi rend="italic">Cambden.</hi>
         Give me more Love or more Disdain 21 - Mr. <hi rend="italic">Tho. Carew,</hi> Gentleman of the Privy Chamber, and Sewer to his late Majesty.
      <hi rend="italic">H.</hi> He that love's a Rosie Cheek 12 - Mr. <hi rend="italic">Carew.</hi>
      <hi rend="italic">I.</hi> I long to sing the Seidge of Troy 27 - Mr. <hi rend="italic">John Berkenhead.</hi>
         If when the Sun at Noon 18 - Mr. <hi rend="italic">Carew.</hi>
         It is not that I love you lesse 22 - Mr. <hi rend="italic">Waller.</hi>
         <hi rend="italic">Imbre lachrymarum largo</hi> 36 - Mr. <hi rend="italic">Thomas Fuller,</hi> Batch. Divinity.
      <hi rend="italic">L.</hi> Ladies who gild the glitt'ring Noon 35 - Mr. <hi rend="italic">Francis Lenton.</hi>
         Lately on yonder swelling Bush 24 - Mr. <hi rend="italic">Waller.</hi>
         Lovely <hi rend="italic">Chloris</hi> though thine eyes 20 - Mr. <hi rend="italic">Henry Reynolds.</hi>
      <hi rend="italic">T.</hi> The Day's return'd 33 - Mr. <hi rend="italic">Berkenhead.</hi>
         Till now I never did believe 16 - Sir <hi rend="italic">Thomas Nevill.</hi>
         Till I beheld fair <hi rend="italic">Cælia's</hi> Face 25 - <hi rend="italic">Francis Finch,</hi> Esquire.
         'Tis true fair <hi rend="italic">Cælia</hi> 29 - Mr. <hi rend="italic">Henry Bathurst.</hi>
         Thou art so Fair and Yong 31 - Mr. <hi rend="italic">Aurelian Townshend.</hi>
         'Tis Wine that inspir's 32 - Lord <hi rend="italic">Broughall.</hi>
         Two hundred minutes are run down 34 - Mr. <hi rend="italic">Berkenhead.</hi>
      <hi rend="italic">V.</hi> Venus redress a wrong 7 - Mr. <hi rend="italic">Cartwright.</hi>
      <hi rend="italic">W.</hi> When thou poor Excommunicate 8 - Mr. <hi rend="italic">Carew</hi>
         When on the Altar of my hand 9 - Mr. <hi rend="italic">Carew.</hi>
         While I listen to thy Voyce 13 - Mr. <hi rend="italic">Waller,</hi>
         <hi rend="italic">Θέλω λέγειν Ἀτρείδας</hi> 26 - <hi rend="italic">Anacreon's Ode,</hi> call'd the Lute.
         <hi rend="italic">Inquel gelato core (TAVOLA)</hi> Last Pag. in the Book - By divers and sundry Authors.
                  <hi rend="italic">Dialogues and Songs for two Voyces.</hi>
        DIstressed Pilgrim, A Dialogue betwixt <hi rend="italic">Cordanus</hi> and an <hi rend="italic">Amorest</hi> <hi rend="italic">Pag.</hi> 1 - Col. <hi rend="italic">Francis Lovelace.</hi>
        Aged man that mowes these Fields, A Dialogue betwixt <hi rend="italic">Time</hi> and a <hi rend="italic">Pilgrim</hi> 3 - Mr. <hi rend="italic">Aurelian Townshend.</hi>
        As <hi rend="italic">Cælia</hi> rested in the shade, A Dialogue betwixt <hi rend="italic">Cleon</hi> and <hi rend="italic">Cælia</hi> 5 - Mr. <hi rend="italic">Tho. Carew.</hi>
        <hi rend="italic">Bacebus I'acchus</hi> fill our brains 9 - Mr. <hi rend="italic">Townshend.</hi>
        Go thou Emblem of my heart 10 - Mr. <hi rend="italic">Harington.</hi>
        O the Fickle state of Lovers 12 - Mr. <hi rend="italic">Francis Quarles.</hi>
        Musick thou Queen of Souls 14 - Mr. <hi rend="italic">Tho. Randolph</hi> of Trinity College <hi rend="italic">Cambridge.</hi>
                  <hi rend="italic">Ayres and Songs for three Voyces.</hi>
        COme <hi rend="italic">Chloris,</hi> hie we to the Bower 16 - Mr. <hi rend="italic">Henry Reynolds.</hi>
        Though my Torment far exceeds 17 - Mr. <hi rend="italic">Harington.</hi>
        If my Mistress fix her Eye 18 - Mr. <hi rend="italic">Harington.</hi>
        Keep on your Vaile 19 - Dr. <hi rend="italic">Stroud.</hi>
        Thou Shepheard whose intentive eye 20 - Mr. <hi rend="italic">Townshend.</hi>
        O now the certain Cause I know 21 - Mr. <hi rend="italic">Cartwright.</hi>
        Sing Fair <hi rend="italic">Clorinda</hi> 22 - Sr. <hi rend="italic">William Davenant.</hi>
        Grieve not Dear Love 24 - <hi rend="italic">John</hi> Earle of <hi rend="italic">Bristoll.</hi>
        Ladyes whose smooth and Dainty Skin. 26 - Mr. <hi rend="italic">Harington.</hi>
       </ab>
</div>
</front>
  <body>
    <pb n="F1v"/>
    <div type="ayres">
    <xi:include href="Dearest_do_not_now_delay_me-L638_1.xml" xpointer="#song8"/>

<xi:include href="Imbre_lachrymarum_largo_Genas_spargo-L638_1.xml" xpointer="#song???"/>
    <head rend="center">FINIS.</head>
  </div type="ayres">
  <div type="dialogues">
    <head rend="center">PASTORALL DIALOGVES.</head>

  </body>
</text>
</TEI>
